<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: investing | John Dreams]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.johnstorey.org/blog/categories/investing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.johnstorey.org/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-31T21:30:05-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.johnstorey.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Storey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Investments on Sale - Again!]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.johnstorey.org/blog/2012/05/04/investments-on-sale-again/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-04T12:13:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.johnstorey.org/blog/2012/05/04/investments-on-sale-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Lately I&rsquo;ve been turning my eye back to my investments, primarily in equities. Well, really, since doing my takes and updating the retirement plan.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m here to say: the news is good for the bargain hunter.</p>

<p>Marc Faber popped up in the Wall Street Journal today with a viewpoint that I believe: the U.S. market can see another 20% decline.</p>

<p>Helping dollar destruction, Bernanke seems poised to do QE3, even if it may be under another name.</p>

<p>Europe is the U.S. 2009 (oh, did I make money in oil futures that year? I did!). Spain is undoubtedly being combed by bargain hunters, but there is likely enough for everyone. With companies that have nice exposure to emerging markets in Latin America.</p>

<p>France is likely to elect Holland to run the place. Can we say an end to austerity in the Euro zone, cheap money everywhere, and more currency destruction.</p>

<p>Yes, I&rsquo;m really thinking alot about commodities again.</p>

<p>Other trends: we are a few years away from Social Security and Medicare running out in the U.S. That is a mega event beyond compare, and to be honest, I&rsquo;m not ready to take advantage of it. Time to make a plan.</p>

<p>There are some relevant factoids that should make any investor step back and reflect. There is lots going on here and values should pop up left and right, if only we can dig them out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
